Guide to the Hope T. Eldridge papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Hope T. Eldridge Papers,
1939-1991
[Bulk Dates: 1950-1956]
Eldridge, Hope T. (Hope Tisdale)
1 linear ft. (2 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1619
9461817
Hope T. Eldridge was a demographer and statistician at the United Nations, who was a victim of the McCarthy-era anti-communist accusations. The collection includes her personal correspondence and documents relating to her dismissal from the U.N.
Biographical Note
Hope Tisdale Eldridge was born June 18, 1904 in Mobile, Alabama. She received her B.A. in English from Barnard College, where she developed an interest in physical education. After receiving her degree from Barnard she attended the Boston Central School of Hygiene and Physical Education where she trained to become a physical education instructor. Eldridge became a professor of physical education at the Women’s College of the University of North Carolina in 1927.
Eldridge held that position until 1938 when she began pursuing a career as a sociologist, both as a research assistant with the sociology department at the University of North Carolina, and through her employment with the North Carolina Works Progress Administration. In 1942 Eldridge took a position with the Census Bureau as a statistician, a post she held until 1947 when she took a position as a statistician for the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. In 1950 Eldridge became the editor of the Demographic Yearbook published by the United Nations.
In October of 1952 Eldridge was ordered to appear before the Internal Security Subcommittee of the United States Senate Judiciary Committee where she was interrogated about her political affiliations and those of her associates. She refused to answer questions that may link her of her acquaintances with communist causes, asserting her first and fifth amendment rights. Her refusal to answer these questions led to her dismissal from her position with the United Nations. She and nineteen other applicants petitioned to be reinstated in their positions, a petition that they ultimately won.
Scope and Content
This collection contains personal correspondence relating to Hope T. Eldridge's dismissal from her position as a United Nations statistician. It also contains legal correspondence and official documentation, including statements, relating to her administrative tribunal following her dismissal from the U.N. This tribunal took place during the McCarthy-era anti-communist accusations in the early 1950s in the United States of America. The collection also includes academic writing, family correspondence, and photographs.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in IV series
Series I: Correspondence, 1939-1986
Series II: Photographs, Undated
Series III: Writings, Undated, 1942-1970
Series IV: U.N. Dismissal, 1952-1991
Subjects
United Nations.; a Eldridge, Hope T. (Hope Tisdale).; Anti-communist movements--United States--20th century.; Correspondence.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Eldridge family Gift
- Series I: Correspondence, 1939-1986
  The bulk of the correspondence dates from 1950-1955 and pertains to her dismissal from the U.N. and her administrative tribunal. Other correspondence pertains to family and personal concerns, some not written or addressed to Hope T. Eldridge.
  - Personal, 1939-1955, (10 folders) (Box 1)
  - Family, 1951-1986 (Box 1)
  - Legal--Official, 1953-1956 (Box 1)
- Series II: Photographs, Undated
  Personal portraits of Hope T. Eldridge, includes one photograph with her husband, C. DeWitt Eldridge.
  - Photographs (Box 1)
- Series III: Writings, Undated, 1942-1970
  Mainly Hope T. Eldridge’s academic writings about demography, including one folder with clippings and correspondence about her 1946 article “Sex Ratio in the U.S.”
  - Academic, 1942-1970 (mostly by H. Eldridge) (Box 2)
  - "Sex Ratio in the U.S.," 1946 (includes correspondence and clippings) (Box 2)
- Series IV: U.N. Dismissal, 1952-1991
  Statements, clippings, and printed material relating to Hope T. Eldridge’s dismissal from the U.N. and her administrative tribunal. There is also material relating more generally to a series of McCarthy-era U.N. dismissals.
  - Hope Eldridge, 1952-1956, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - General (contains book) (Box 2)
  - General, 1952-1991